<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A theater of the planetary houres for all dayes of the yeare VVherein may be gathered from the earth, vnder the cœlestiall influences, divers sorts of hearbs, rootes, leaves, barkes, flowers, fruits, seedes, stones, animals, &amp;c. for the vse of physick: whereby both suddenly, and happily infirmities may be cured. The evils too are set downe, that happen, and are caused by the seuen plannets: the friendship and hatred betwixt them: the sunne rising; and to finde the determinate houre of it. A worke not onely curious and delightfull, but likewise necessary for physitians, and all curious spirits. Composed by George Simotta a Grecian, of Constantinople, spagirick physitian, to Monsieur, brother to his Majestie of France. Translated out of Greeke, into French, and now into English, fitted to our calculation.</title>
            <author>Simotta, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852627</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1008:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A theater of the planetary houres for all dayes of the yeare VVherein may be gathered from the earth, vnder the cœlestiall influences, divers sorts of hearbs, rootes, leaves, barkes, flowers, fruits, seedes, stones, animals, &amp;c. for the vse of physick: whereby both suddenly, and happily infirmities may be cured. The evils too are set downe, that happen, and are caused by the seuen plannets: the friendship and hatred betwixt them: the sunne rising; and to finde the determinate houre of it. A worke not onely curious and delightfull, but likewise necessary for physitians, and all curious spirits. Composed by George Simotta a Grecian, of Constantinople, spagirick physitian, to Monsieur, brother to his Majestie of France. Translated out of Greeke, into French, and now into English, fitted to our calculation.</title>
                  <author>Simotta, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By August. Matthewes, and are to be solde by George Baker, neere Charing-Crosse, at the signe of the White Lyon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Greek original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Magic, mystic, and spagiric --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A THEATER OF THE PLANE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARY HOVRES FOR ALL DAYES OF THE YEARE.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Wherein may be gathered from the earth, vnder the Coeleſtiall influences, divers ſorts of hearbs, rootes, leaves, barkes, flowers, fruits, ſeedes, ſtones, animals, &amp;c. for the vſe of Phyſick: whereby both ſuddenly, and happily infirmities may be Cured.</p>
            <p>The evils too are ſet downe, that happen, and are cauſed by the ſeuen Plannets: The friendſhip and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred betwixt them: the Sunne riſing; and to finde the determinate houre of it.</p>
            <p>A worke not onely curious and delightfull, but likewiſe neceſſary for Phyſitians, and all curious ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Compoſed by <hi>George Simotta</hi> a Grecian, of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, Spagirick</hi> Phyſitian, to Monſieur, brother to his Majeſtie of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Greeke, into French, and now into Engliſh, fitted to our Calculation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Auguſt. Matthewes,</hi> and are to be ſolde by GEORGE BAKER, neere Charing Croſſe, at the Signe of the White Lyon. 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17957:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17957:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Sir ROBERT AETON, Secretary to the Queenes moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SJR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſume to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with a ſmall thing, which ſtands in neede of a Patron of ſuch worth as your ſelf, conſidering that both this time and place, are ſo much giuen to callumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, cenſure, and depraue, euen the beſt of Works of what nature ſo euer. I craue your worthy Patronage, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it is a Stranger lately come from
<pb facs="tcp:17957:3"/> France, put into this Engliſh habite by one which was ſometime yours, and ſent thus into publique view by him, that by your daily and frequent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours you haue made your, though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Seruant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEORGE BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17957:3"/>
            <head>A THEATER OF THE PLANETARY HOVRES FOR ALL THE DAYES OF THE YEARE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is divine Majeſtie out of the inevacuable ſource of his vncreated wiſedome, by his infinite providence, in the Creation of this great vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, did eſtabliſh all the creatures for his glory, and the benefit of men. In ſo much that the earth, his foo ſtoole, embelliſhed with ſo many beautifull creatures, doth abound in plants, hearbs, trees, ſeedes, barkes, woods, gummes, iuices, mettalls, mineralls, and demy-mineralls, All, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith in the firſt of his Geneſis, <hi>Vt ijs ſubinde ad propulſandos morbos vtere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab Adam propagata ſoboles,</hi> That <hi>Adams</hi> proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie might vſe them to preſerue health: And the living creatures in ſo many ſeverall kindes have peopled the Sea, filled the ayre, and inhabited the earth vnder the government of men, to whom,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17957:4"/> as to their Soveraignes, they ought to be as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: and the heavens, repleniſhed with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand glittering lights, the cover of this lower world, by their motions and light, being gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the commandement of the ſupreame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſend downe their powers on men, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences moving; the opinions of ſacred Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians, as <hi>Richardus</hi> in his ſecond booke, <hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>queſt.</hi> 3. and alſo Saint <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> and Saint <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> who will, that the higheſt or Empyreall hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, doth infuſe ſome effects into our lower earth. It is moſt certaine that the ſupreame Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath ordained the heavens, as all the other creatures, not onely for mens preſent benefit, but for that to come; that if the heavens did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe on vs, it were enough to deſtroy that moſt great principle of our Religion. And <hi>Damaſ.</hi> in his 3. booke, <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. ſaith in this behalfe, <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibile eſt aliquam ſubſtantiam expertem eſſe naturali operatione, vſui hominum conference, ergo &amp;c.</hi> It is impoſſible, that any ſubſtance can bee voyde of ſome naturall operation, conducing to the profit of men, therefore &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Theologians gather from the heavens three ſorts of influences appropriated to the three faculties of our immortall ſoule: The ſtarrie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with all the firſt and wandring ſtarres, powre their influences into the Vegetative; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyreall into the Reaſonable; and the Chriſtaline, or firſt mover, infuſe into the Senſitive; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, none of theſe influences can force our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17957:4"/> although the heavens ſend them the one by their motions, the others by their light, and the others by their vertue: So the Empyreall heaven, without moving its ſelfe, ſendeth downe its vertue here belowe, notwithſtanding that it be diſtant from vs ſo farre, that, according to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> in his booke, <hi>De imagine mundi,</hi> from the earth to the firmament, there are three hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, one hundreth and twenty five leagues. And from that, to the Empyreall heaven, are, ten hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth millions of leagues: But to ſay truth (if it be not by revelation from God) no certaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure can be determined. I conclude, <hi>A majore ad minus,</hi> from the greater to the leſſer, that, ſince the influences doe deſcend from ſuch a height, by a more ſtrong reaſon may they come from the heavens, that are neere vs; all which influences are not in the heavens by their nature, but by their effects, as the Aſtrologians ſay: If <hi>Saturne</hi> be colde, the cauſe proceedeth from his motion, which is ſlowe, and lingring, and for that he is ſo farre diſtant from vs, and doth not end his courſe but in thirty yeares, according to the ſame <hi>Beda:</hi> Now, the other planets, that are of more ſpeedy motion, and doe (as it were) with a ſwift, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid courſe, and in little time, make their Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are hot, and dry; as <hi>Sol,</hi> and <hi>Mars:</hi> But what availeth it vs to bring ſo farre fetcht rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? Since that, ſo neere vs, theſe effects are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto vs ſo evidently, in the foure ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the living creatures, in the plants, in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17957:5"/> the ſea, in the ayre, in cutting, ſawing, gathering, grafting, and over all the creatures: So that if man know not the reaſon of theſe things, hee ought to ſeeke it in the myracles of nature. To the end then, that every one may the better know, how to make vſe of theſe operations, even in matter of Phyſick, they muſt chuſe the dayes, the houres, the plants, vnder ſuch favourable aſpects, and agreeable influences of the Starres, as can, by their agreeable vertue, give health vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſicke; for the Planets and fixed Starres, doe cauſe all infirmities: wherefore they muſt chuſe the Planet, that is enemie to that Planet that brought forth that evill; and ſo, by the contrary effect, put it away and diſſolue it. Wherefore <hi>Arnauld</hi> of <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> in his booke, <hi>De ſimplicibus Medicina,</hi> ſaith theſe words, <hi>Ad hoc vt ipſae herbae, flores, radices, &amp; ſemina, habeant ſingularem virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, &amp; proprietatem ad morbos tollendos, ſunt Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda ſecundum diverſa ſigna Zodiaci, quia citius &amp; foelicius operantur in morbis.</hi> Moreover, that the very hearbs, flowers, rootes, and ſeeds, may have a ſingular vertue, and quality to remove diſeaſes, they are to be gathered according to the ſeverall ſignes of the Zodiack, becauſe ſo they doe more ſpeedily and ſuccesfully worke on diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe, firſt, I have thought good to ſet downe the Planets in order, and the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are cauſed by them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the certaine houre of the Sunnes riſing every day in the yeare, to the end that you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17957:5"/> may eaſily finde out the houre wherein you are to gather or take the plants, ſtones, or animals, to cure your infirmities.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I haue ſet downe too, the vnequall Planetary houre, as well of the day as of the night, whereby you may know certainly what Planet ſhall governe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, you have in like order, the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and enmity of the Planets; which are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies amongſt them; that you may the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily finde the Planet, enemie to it that ſhall cauſe the diſeaſe, and in the ſame houre that is gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it, the infirmity may be cured.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the cures of all vſuall diſeaſes are ſet downe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What the infirmities and diſeaſes are, which are cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by every of the Planets.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aturne</hi> governing, doth cauſe all cold diſeaſes, as the Gowt in the feete, Leproſie, the Scab, the Palſie, <hi>Quartane</hi> Agues, the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Catarres, Diffluxions on the Lungs, Conſumptions, Coughes, and the like cold and Melancholick infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> cauſeth the Cramp, ſtupidneſſe, infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17957:6"/> of the lyuer, the head-ach, paines in the ſhoulders, the Squinance, Apoplexie, the <hi>Cardia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca paſsio</hi> or heart ſickneſſe, the bloudy flux, and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> cauſeth burning Feavers, Impoſtumes, tertian, quotidian, and intermitting Agues, Saint <hi>Antonies</hi> fires, Carbuncles, Fiſtulaes, diſſenteries, and the like hot diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> cauſeth defluxions and rhewmes that fall on the eyes, coldneſſe of the ſtomack, and lyver, ſwoundings, red choller, the Catarre, bliſters on the Matrice, and ſuch other infirmities on the lower parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> cauſeth the Scab, the French Pox, the Lienterick Flux, Paſſions and Suffocations of the Matrice, and all other diſeaſes of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercurius</hi> cauſeth hoarceneſſe, all paſſions of the ſenſes, the falling ſickneſſe, common impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of the tongue, and its paſſions, obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Gall, and all melancholick evils.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> cauſeth the Palſey, the Chollick, the termes, the Dropſie, Phlegmatick impoſtumes, and all the infirmities that proceede from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the veynes.</p>
               <p>Now, to cure any of theſe infirmities infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and not as ſome Phyſicians proceede, <hi>Saluo ſemper iure calculi,</hi> keeping ſtill a iuſt account, it is requiſite to make vſe of Aſtrologie, &amp; the aſpects of the ſtarres and of their influences, and that is to be vnderſtood <hi>in cura regulari,</hi> in a regular cure,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17957:6"/> and not <hi>coactâ practicâ,</hi> by forced practiſe Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch a caſe, as <hi>Hip.</hi> in his fourth booke <hi>Aphor.</hi> 1. willeth vs, <hi>Medicari in valdè acutis morbis cadem die ſi materia turgeat, tardari in his malum est,</hi> To vſe remedies in very ſharpe diſeaſes on the firſt day, if the matter abound; Delayes in theſe are dangerous. Yet <hi>Menardus</hi> in his Epiſtles in the like caſe ſaith, That, <hi>potiùs lotium inſpiciendum quàm aſtra,</hi> The vrine is rather to be looked into then the ſtars. But that is to be vnderſtood, for let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of blood, and purging the body. But as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning other locall or topicall remedies, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to obſerue the Planetarie houres. And for this purpoſe, we muſt conſider by what Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net the infirmity is cauſed, then take the hearbe, or flower, ſeedes, rootes, or ſuch other things, in ſuch an houre as ſhall be governed by the Planet, that is enemy to the cauſer of the evill: <hi>Quia contraria contrarijs curantur.</hi> Contraries are cured by their contraries.</p>
               <p>Now, for to know the certaine houre of ſuch a Planet, you ſhall marke at what houre of that day the Sun ſhall riſe, attributing ever the firſt houre of the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en-riſing, to the Planet that beares the name of that day: As, on Sunday the firſt houre ſhall be the houre of <hi>Sol</hi> or the Sun: On Monday the firſt houre, ſhall be the houre of <hi>Luna</hi> or the Moon: On Tueſ. the firſt houre, ſhal be the houre of <hi>Mars:</hi> On Wed. <hi>Mercurie</hi> governeth the firſt houre: On Thurſ. <hi>Iupiter:</hi> Fridayes firſt houre <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ruleth: And on the firſt of Saturday <hi>Saturne.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17957:7"/> After the certaine knowledge of the Planet, that governeth the firſt houre of the Sunne-riſing on every day, you muſt follow the naturall order of the Planets, attributing ſtill the ſucceeding Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to every ſucceeding houre. The naturall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Planets is this, <hi>Saturnus, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercurius, Luna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Planet governour of each day in the weeke, is as followeth:
<table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>The dayes of the weeke,</cell>
                        <cell>The Planet gover.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sunday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sol,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Monday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Luna,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tueſday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Mars,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Wedneſday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Mercurius,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Thurſday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Friday,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Venus,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Saturday.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saturnus.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The dayes whereon it is dangerous to let bloud.</head>
                  <item>Ianuary. 11. 14. 16. 21. 26. 30.</item>
                  <item>February. 26. 27. 28.</item>
                  <item>March. 26. 27. 28.</item>
                  <item>April. 15. 17. 25.</item>
                  <item>May. 17. 25. 30.</item>
                  <item>Iune. 18.</item>
                  <item>Iuly. 23. 26.</item>
                  <item>Auguſt. 28. 30.</item>
                  <item>September. 25. 28.</item>
                  <item>October. 16. 26.</item>
                  <item>Novemb. 25. 26.</item>
                  <item>Decem. 16. 17. 21.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17957:7"/>
                  <head>The dayes whereon Phyſick being taken, doth not purge the body.</head>
                  <item>Ianuary. 19. 27.</item>
                  <item>February. 14. 26.</item>
                  <item>March. 13. 23.</item>
                  <item>April. 10.</item>
                  <item>May. 7. 17.</item>
                  <item>Iune. 04. 12.</item>
                  <item>Iuly. 17. 20.</item>
                  <item>Auguſt. 14. 18.</item>
                  <item>September. 10. 17.</item>
                  <item>October. 8. 16.</item>
                  <item>November. 5. 12.</item>
                  <item>December. 2. 10.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The dayes whereon Phyſick provoketh Vomiting.</head>
                  <item>Ianuary. 1. 18. 24.</item>
                  <item>February. 14. 28.</item>
                  <item>March. 13. 22.</item>
                  <item>April. 10.</item>
                  <item>May. 7. 17.</item>
                  <item>Iune. 4. 11.</item>
                  <item>Iuly. 17. 20.</item>
                  <item>Auguſt. 6. 7. 24.</item>
                  <item>September. 7. 23.</item>
                  <item>October. 1. 18. 27.</item>
                  <item>November. 15.</item>
                  <item>December. 4. 13.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17957:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> At what houre the Sunne riſeth in every day of the yeare.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt muſt be vnderſtood, that in every houre are 60. minutes. Now for to declare this more briefely, you have heere ſet down the certaine houre where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in on the 10. 20. and 30. day of every moneth the Sun doth riſe. And if you would know the certaine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of every the vnexpreſſed dayes; divide the intermitted minutes proportionably to every of the dayes that are not mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Ianuary.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Houres.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Minutes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. day the Sunne riſeth at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>February.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17957:8"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>March.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. day the Sunne riſeth at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Aprill.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>May.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Iune.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Iuly.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17957:9"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>September.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. day the Sunne riſeth at</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>October.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>November.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>December.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 10. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 20. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The 30. &amp;c. at</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The vnequall Planetary houres of the day and night, Calculated according to the <hi>Ephimerides.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="table_of_planetary_hours">
                  <head>The houres of the day.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sunday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sol,1</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus,2</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars,7</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol,8</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus,9</hi> 
                              <hi>Mer.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17957:9"/>
                     <item>Monday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Luna,1</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter,3</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars,4</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol,5</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter,10</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars,11</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tueſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mars.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wedneſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mercu.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Thurſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iupit.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Friday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Venus.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Saturday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Saturn.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_planetary_hours">
                  <head>The houres of the night.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sunday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iupit.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17957:10"/>
                     <item>Monday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Venus.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tueſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Saturn.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Wedneſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sol,1</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus,2</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Thurſday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Luna,1</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter,3</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars,4</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol,5</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter,10</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars,11</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Friday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mars,1</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol,2</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus,3</hi> 
                              <hi>Mer.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.10</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Luna.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Saturday.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mercu.1</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.2</hi> 
                              <hi>Saturn.3</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupiter.4</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.5</hi> 
                              <hi>Sol.6</hi> 
                              <hi>Venus.7</hi> 
                              <hi>Mercu.8</hi> 
                              <hi>Lun.9</hi> 
                              <hi>Satur.10.</hi> 
                              <hi>Iupit.11</hi> 
                              <hi>Mars.12</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17957:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Which are friendly Planets one to another.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ol</hi> is a friend to <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> is friendly to <hi>Iupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Saturne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> is a friend to <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> is friendly to <hi>Iupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> is friendly to <hi>Sol, Luna, Mercury, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Saturne.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Planets that are enemies one to another.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol</hi> is enemie to <hi>Mars, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Luna.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luna</hi> is enemy to <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercurius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> is enemie to <hi>Luna, Mercurie,</hi> and <hi>Saturne:</hi> but moſt to <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercurie</hi> is enemie to <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> and <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iupiter</hi> is enemie to <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> is enemie to <hi>Saturne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="secrets">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17957:11"/>
            <head>Excellent and approved Secrets; with the manner how, and when they are to be taken, and made, vnder the Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Starres, whereby the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing infirmities may in very ſhort time be cured.</head>
            <div n="1" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Againſt the headache.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vpiter</hi> cauſeth this evill: Take the hearbe called Pſilio or Flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> his enemie; ſtampe it, and mingle it with vinegar, and apply it to the forehead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Againſt Frenzies or ſharpe Feavers.</head>
               <p>Theſe diſeaſes are cauſed by <hi>Mars:</hi> Take therefore in the houre of <hi>Luna, Mercury, Saturne, Sol,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter</hi> his enemies, the milke of any beaſt, except that of Goates; boyle it, and with the skinne that ſwimmes above it, bathe all your head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="secret">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17957:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To cure the Falling ſickneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> doth cauſe this evill: Wherefore in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, you muſt get a Woolfe, and kill it in any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid houres; take the lights of it, and boyle them in red wine, adding thereto ſome Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick ſpices, and when they are ſufficiently boyled, give them the Patient to eate, and hee ſhall be well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Againſt weakeneſſes and dimneſſe in the eyes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> is the Author of theſe infirmities: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars,</hi> his enemie, the hearbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Euphragia, or Eyebright, beaten to powder, and mingle it with the yelk of an egge, or wine, and lay it on the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> To cure the waterings and fluxes in the eyes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> is the cauſe of this evill: Take therefore in the houre of <hi>Mars,</hi> his enemie, the ſlymie and gummie ſubſtance of the Snaile, with which you ſhall mingle, Mirrh, Aloes, and Maſtick, and then apply it to the temples of the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="secret">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17957:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To take away Carnoſities in the noſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> doth cauſe this evill: To cure which, in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> his enemie, you muſt take the hearbe Dragon, and preſſe out the iuyce of it, and mingle it with the milke of wilde Fennell, and any ſort of Gall, that yee may moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently come by: Then the powder of Nettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede, Southernwood, Hellebore, and Cypres: mingle all together, and let them be often ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp into the noſe, and it will infallibly cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Againſt bleeding at the noſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſeth this infirmity: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> his enemie, Balauſti, or Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate buds, and ſtampe them to powder, and mingle them with the white of an egge, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the noſthrils.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Againſt paines and puſhes in the eares.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> cauſeth theſe: Take in the houre of <hi>Sol,</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> his enemies, the flower of the Ivie; boyle it in oyle, and powre it in the eares, and it taketh away thoſe paines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="secret">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17957:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Againſt deafeneſſe, and buſsings in the eares.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> is Author hereof: Therefore in the houre of <hi>Sol</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, take a Hare, kill it, and waſh the gall of it, with which yee ſhall mingle the powder of blacke Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore; put it in the eares, and it cureth thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> To take away Bliſters and hackes on the lips.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> doth likewiſe cauſe theſe evills: Take therefore in the houre of <hi>Sol</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, Litarge of ſilver, Mirrh, Ginger, of each an equall quantity; beate them into very fine powder, then with Virgine Wax, Honey, and ordinary Oyle, you ſhall make an Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſpread it on any fine cloath, and apply it to the lips.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> To eaſe the paine of the Tooth-ache.</head>
               <p>This evill too is cauſed by <hi>Mercury:</hi> Take in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, two graines of the ſeede of <hi>Acace,</hi> of <hi>Opium, Ioſchtamum,</hi> of each two drachmes, mixe them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17957:13"/> with wine, and role them vp like Pills: hold one of theſe betwixt your teeth, and it will quickly aſſwage the paine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> To make hollow or pained teeth to fall of themſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> is the cauſer of theſe: Take in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, the branches of wilde Olives, boyle them in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuice till it become as thick as honey; apply it to the tainted tooth, and it will cauſe it fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> To ſtrengthen the teeth.</head>
               <p>This infirmity is cauſed by <hi>Mercury:</hi> Take in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, the skinnes of Pomegranates, Ireos, burn'd Salt, of each two parts, of Gall two parts, of Mirrh one part; let them boyle in wine, with which waſh your teeth often.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> To facilitate the growth of teeth in young children without danger of death.</head>
               <p>This evill is cauſed of <hi>Mercury:</hi> Take in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> his enemies, a Hare, kill it, take out the braines of it, boyle them, and rub the teeth often with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="secret">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17957:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>15.</hi> The Squinance.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter</hi> is Author of this evill: Take a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtrangle it with a double threed, and in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> his enemie bathe it in Rattes bloud, which will cauſe the body of it to riſe, then apply it to the necke, and it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To ſtop bloud.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſeth this evill: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, Pomegranate buds, Hypociſtis, and Verbaſcum or Mullet, ſtampe them, and preſſe out the iuice of them, and (as occaſion ſhall require) adminiſter to the Patient a ſpoonefull at a time, well mingled with Sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>17.</hi> To helpe infirmities of the ſtomack.</head>
               <p>Theſe are cauſed by <hi>Sol:</hi> You ſhall take in the houre of <hi>Mars, Mercury</hi> or <hi>Luna</hi> his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the hearbe called Baulme, and Pimper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and eate faſting ſuch quantity of them, as you ſhall pleaſe; for even whilſt you doe it, it comforts the ſtomack, openeth obſtructions, and ſtrengtheneth the weakenes of the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="secret">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17957:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>18.</hi> To take away paines in the ſtomack.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> cauſeth theſe paines; Wherefore in the houre of <hi>Mars, Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Luna,</hi> his enemies, Take a Henne, kill it, and take out the little thinne skinne that is in the little belly of it, make it into powder, and give it to be drunke with wine. An excellent remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>19.</hi> To cure inflamed livers.</head>
               <p>This evill is bred vnder <hi>Iupiter:</hi> Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> his enemie, the hearb of the ſtarry Thiſtle, preſſe out the juice, and give halfe a glaſſe full to be drunke at a time, and it will worke an admirable effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Againſt the Dropſie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſeth this evill: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> his enemies, a Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, kill it, and give the diſeaſed perſon two glaſſe fulls of the bloud of it to drinke, and it will vndoubtedly cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="secret">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17957:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>21.</hi> To cure the yellow Iaundize.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> doth cauſe this diſeaſe: Take in the houre of <hi>Sol, Luna,</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> his enemies, the ſeede of Roſemary, make it into powder, and mingle it with the juice of Pentaſilion or Cinquefoyle, to what quantity ſhall pleaſe you, and it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>22.</hi> To helpe obſtructions, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Milt or Spleene.</head>
               <p>This diſeaſe doth <hi>Luna</hi> cauſe: Wherefore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her enemies, you ſhall take Bole Armoniack, diſſolved in Vinegar, and drinke the weight of two drachmes of it at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>23.</hi> The ſtone in the kidnies.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſeth this evill: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars,</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, Pellitory of the wall, and give the juice thereof to be drunke with wine: it purgeth the kidnies, and will breake the ſtone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="secret">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17957:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>24.</hi> To helpe the difficulty in making of water.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> cauſeth this infirmity: Wherefore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her enemies, take the leaves and ſeedes of Trifolie, and the ſeede of Southernwood; boyle them in water, to which decoction adde a Spaniſh flye, without head, feete, or wings, beaten into powder, a culouſly full whereof being drunke, doth mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoone provoke Vrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>25.</hi> The ſtone in the bladder.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> doth cauſe this diſeaſe: Take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſome Scorpions, put them in a new ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pot, that hath a narrow mouth, and ſet it in an Oven that is not too hot the ſpace of ſix houres; then take them out, and ſtampe them ſmall; and take one drachme at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>26.</hi> To eaſe the paine of the Chollick.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> cauſeth this evill: In the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her enemies, take the ſpriggs, and fruit of the Bay tree, beat them into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and give the Patient two drachmes of it to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17957:15"/> be drunk in Hypocras, and in effect it will take away the paine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>27.</hi> The Bloudie-Flux or Dyſenterie.</head>
               <p>This evill being cauſed by <hi>Luna,</hi> you muſt take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Pomegranate buds, and Hypociſtis, made into powder, and give two drachmes thereof to bee drunke in red wine, or Pome-Citerne water. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Againſt difficulties in Child bearing.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> being the cauſer of theſe impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the houre of <hi>Saturne</hi> her enemie, you muſt take ſweet Baſill, beate it into powder, and give it to be drunke with good wine, and ſhe will be delivered inſtantly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>29.</hi> To provoke the tearmes and ſecondine, or after-birth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> cauſeth this infirmitie: Therefore in the houre of <hi>Mars,</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> her enemies, take Agrimonie, ſtampe it with the ſeedes of of Montaine Smallage, and adminiſter two
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17957:16"/> drachmes thereof to bee drunke in Maydenhaire water, and their deſire ſhall bee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>30.</hi> To ſtop the immoderate Flux of the tearmes, and to contract the mouth of the Matrice.</head>
               <p>This evill being cauſed by <hi>Venus,</hi> you muſt in the houre of <hi>Saturne,</hi> her enemy, take the middle skinne of the Cheſnut, the skinne of a Pomegranate, pound them all very ſmall, and in the wine of Quinces, adminiſter one drachme to be drunk, as often as occaſions ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To helpe chops in the feete.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> cauſeth this: Take therefore in the houre of <hi>Mars, Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Luna</hi> his enemies, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris Nutts beate into powder, then mingle them with the juice of ſome ſprigges, of the ſame tree, whilſt they are greene, which being applied playſter-wayes, taketh away all chops in the feete.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>32.</hi> To cure the Hemoroides.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> Cauſing this evill: In the houre of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17957:16"/> 
                  <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury,</hi> her enemies, Swines bread muſt be layed to the fundament, and it cureth them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>33.</hi> To helpe all paines in the ioynts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> being the prime cauſe of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; In the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, the diſeaſed muſt take a Henne of foure yeares olde, kill it, and fill it full of Wormewood, and let it boyle in three quarts of water, till the halfe thereof be conſumed away, and with the remainder let him annoint the places affected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Tertian Agues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> doth cauſe this Feaver; wherefore in the houre of <hi>Luna, Mercury, Saturne, Sol,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> his enemies, take the hearb called Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, made in powder, whereof you ſhall give the quantity of two drachmes to bee drunke faſting, in wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Quartane Agues.</head>
               <p>This Feaver is cauſed of <hi>Saturne:</hi> take therefore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, Mirrh, and Caſtoreum, of each a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17957:17"/> drachme, made into powder, and give it to be drunk faſting with wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>36.</hi> To take away all markes of the ſmall Pox.</head>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Mars</hi> doth cauſe, wherefore in the houre of <hi>Luna, Mercury, Saturne,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter,</hi> his enemies, you muſt take Lytarge, the rootes of dry reedes, the meale of Chick Peaſon, the meale of Rice, and old Garlick, ſtampe all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and mingle them with the oyle of ſweet Almonds, Sheepes ſewet melted; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with annoint your face, and let it remaine ſo all night, and in the morning waſh it off with warme water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>37.</hi> To cure the Kings evill.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> doth cauſe this evill: Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury,</hi> Caper rootes, ſtamp them, and apply them plaiſter-wayes to the place affected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>38.</hi> To heale all wounds.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> being the cauſer of theſe evils; you muſt take in the houre of <hi>Luna, Mercury, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the hearbe Savine beate into
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17957:17"/> powder, which being mingled with honey, and applyed to the wounds, will heale them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>39.</hi> To cure the Scab and Leproſie.</head>
               <p>Theſe evils <hi>Saturne</hi> doth cauſe; wherefore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, take Ivie, boyle it, make a Bath of it, and bathe your whole body in it, and it taketh away the infirmity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>40.</hi> To take away all Cornes on the feete.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> cauſing theſe evils; Take in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> his enemies, the barke of the Willow tree, burne it, and mingle the aſhes thereof with very ſtrong Vinegar, which plaiſter you ſhall lay on your Cornes, and it will eate them out by the roote.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>41.</hi> For Cankers.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> cauſeth this evill, wherefore in the houre of <hi>Luna, Saturne,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter:</hi> take the branches of white Sage, and the rootes of Dragon, preſſe out their juice, and mingle them with honey, and apply them to the evill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="secret">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17957:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Againſt Fiſtulaes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> being the cauſer hereof; take in any of the houres afore-ſaid of his enemies, the <hi>Flower de lis</hi> roote, make it into powder, mingle it with the powder of burn'd Oyſter ſhells, and Swines ſeame, and apply it to the Fiſtula.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="secret">
               <head>
                  <hi>43.</hi> A preſervative againſt the Gowt in the feete.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> is cauſer of this evill: Take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the houre of <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> the hearbe called Fetherfewle, ſtampe it, and mingle it with the yolke of an egge, and fryed in the faſhion of a Tanſie, which being eaten faſting, doth moſt ſurely preſerue from the Gowt in the feete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="secret">
               <head>To know whether one that is ſick ſhall live or die.</head>
               <p>Divers are the judgements that ſome men give, whether a ſicke perſon ſhall live or die; But I will here ſet downe a preſent infallible ſigne, whereby every one may be aſſured, and give certaine judgement of it. Take a Nettle, and lay it in the Vrine of the diſeaſed perſon, immediatly after he ſhall have made water, ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17957:18"/> that the water bee pure from any other ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with it; Then let the Nettle remaine therein the ſpace of 24. houres; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after if the Nettle be found dry and withered, it is a ſigne of death; but if it continue greene, it is a ſigne of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="secret">
               <head>An admirable Secret to preſerue vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in health, often vſed by <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth.</head>
               <p>Take in the houre of <hi>Sol,</hi> who is Author of life, foure branches of Rue, nine Iuniper ſeeds, a Walnut, a dry Figge, and a little ſalt, pound all together in a Morter, and every other mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eate a little of it faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
